Guide to the Czesław Miłosz Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1934-2000; Series II; 30.44; (74 boxes)
  - Prose
    - Essays and Other Shorter Works of Prose
      - Polish
        - "Brognart: Moja opowieść przy szklance," draft, holograph, corrected, and background material, including notes, clippings and correspondence, 1942-1952, undated (Box 113, Folder 1599)
        - Była raz kultura: rozmowy z Zofią Hertz title>, by Iza Chruślińska (Foreword by Miłosz), printout, corrected, 1993 (Box 113, Folder 1600)
        - "Co śmiem myśleć," draft, holograph, corrected, 1960 (Box 113, Folder 1601)
        - "Co to jest epifania?," draft, typescript, 1990s (Box 113, Folder 1602)
        - "Czechowicz – to jest o poezji między wojnami," draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1954 (Box 113, Folder 1603)
        - "Czy będzie powieść?" draft, copy of typescript, corrected, 1990s (Box 113, Folder 1604)
        - "Dar nieprzyzwyczajenia (Nowy poeta polski)" (on Miron Białoszewski), draft, typescript carbon, 1956 (Box 113, Folder 1605)
        - "Dialog o Wilnie" (to Tomas Venclova), draft, typescript, corrected, 1978 (Box 113, Folder 1606)
          Also printed as "Do Tomasa Venclovy"
        - "Diariusz paryski," copies of 1960 printed version, undated (Box 113, Folder 1607)
        - "Dlaczego nie piszę powieści," draft, copy of 1984 holograph, corrected, undated (Box 113, Folder 1608)
        - "Do Kisiela," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1946 (Box 113, Folder 1609)
        - "Do naszych czytelników w kraju," draft, holograph, corrected, 1957 (Box 113, Folder 1610)
          Letter to the readers of Kultura.
        - "Doktorat," draft, holograph, corrected, 1953 (Box 113, Folder 1611)
        - "Dostojewski i Sartre," draft, holograph, corrected, 1982 (Box 113, Folder 1612)
        - "Dostojewski teraz," draft, holograph, corrected, 1991 (Box 113, Folder 1613)
        - "Duncan," (from Abecadło ) draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1996 (Box 113, Folder 1614)
        - "Duże cienie," partial draft, holograph, corrected, 1972 (Box 113, Folder 1615)
        - "Dwa końce kija," draft, holograph, 1956 (Box 113, Folder 1616)
        - "Dwa pożegnania" (on Wiktor Sukiennicki and Jerzy Andrzejewski), drafts, holograph and copy of typescript, corrected, circa 1983 (Box 113, Folder 1617)
        - "Dwa wiersze z komentarzem ('Do polityka'; 'Siegfried i Erika')," draft, holograph, corrected, 1952 (Box 113, Folder 1618)
        - "Dwie książki o wojnie" (Review of Last of the conquerors by William Gardner Smith and The naked and the dead by Norman Mailer), typescript carbon, 1949 (Box 113, Folder 1619)
        - "Dwie opowieści," typescript, circa 1962 (Box 113, Folder 1620)
        - "Dwight Macdonald," draft, holograph, circa 1954 (Box 113, Folder 1621)
        - "Dwustronne porachunki," draft, holograph, corrected, 1964 (Box 114, Folder 1622)
        - "Dykcjonarz wileńskich ulic," draft, holograph, corrected, 1967 (Box 114, Folder 1623)
        - "Dzieci Europy," typescript, 1940s (Box 114, Folder 1624)
        - Epochos sąmoningumo poezija, edited by J. Kékštas (introduction by Miłosz, Polish language version), draft, typescript carbon, corrected, circa 1955 (Box 114, Folder 1625)
        - "Gdyby to można było powiedzieć," draft, typescript, copies of typescript, and copy of 1991 printed version, 1970s, 1991 (Box 114, Folder 1626)
        - "Granice sztuki," offprint, 1957 (Box 114, Folder 1627)
        - "Gwiazda Wilsona," draft, typescript, corrected, 1948 (Box 114, Folder 1628)
        - "Henry Miller czyli dno," draft, holograph, corrected, 1948 (Box 114, Folder 1629)
        - "Historia londyńska," draft, holograph, corrected, 1945-1946 (Box 114, Folder 1630)
        - History of Polish Literature (remarks on progress), drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected, 1967 (Box 114, Folder 1631)
        - "Joseph Conrad heute" (Polish language version), draft, holograph, corrected, 1957 (Box 114, Folder 1632)
        - "Joseph Conrad in Polish eyes" (Polish language version), draft, holograph, corrected, 1957 (Box 114, Folder 1633)
        - "Josif Brodski," draft, printout, 1993 (Box 114, Folder 1634)
        - "Józef Czechowicz," draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1954 (Box 114, Folder 1635)
        - "Jubilat," copy of typescript, corrected, 1980s (Box 114, Folder 1636)
        - "Kilka problemów osobistych," draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1954 (Box 114, Folder 1637)
          Translated from French ("Quelques problèmes personnels").
        - "Kilka żądań," drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected, 1962 (Box 114, Folder 1638)
        - "Kohelet," draft, holograph, corrected, 1970s (Box 114, Folder 1639)
        - "Komentarz do 'Ody do Stalina' Osipa Mandelsztama," copy of printed version, undated (Box 114, Folder 1640)
        - "Komentarz do 'Poematu dla dorosłych'," draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1955 (Box 114, Folder 1641)
        - "Kongres poetów," draft, holograph, corrected, 1952 or 1953 (Box 114, Folder 1642)
        - "Konstanty: polskie tło," drafts, holograph and copy of typescript, corrected, 1987 (Box 114, Folder 1643)
        - "Korniszonizm," typescript carbon and holograph, 1944, 1959 (Box 114, Folder 1644)
        - "Kronika krajowa," draft, copy of typescript, 1980s (Box 114, Folder 1645)
        - "Kronika litewska," draft, copy of typescript, 1980s (Box 114, Folder 1646)
        - "Księga mickiewiczowska," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1953 (Box 114, Folder 1647)
        - "Kwestia ciągłości," draft, holograph, 1960 (Box 114, Folder 1648)
        - "List Czesława Miłosza do Jana Lebensteina," draft, holograph, corrected, 1985 (Box 114, Folder 1649)
        - "Listy Iwaszkiewicza," draft, printout, undated (Box 114, Folder 1650)
        - "Listy od Niemców," draft, holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 114, Folder 1651)
        - "Literatura amerykańska w r. 1948," drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 114, Folder 1652)
        - "Literatura po dziesięciu latach," draft, holograph, corrected, 1955 (Box 115, Folder 1653)
        - "Liturgia Efraima," draft, holograph and copy of 1968 printed version, 1968, undated (Box 115, Folder 1654-1655)
        - "Litwa," copy of 1991 printed version (Box 115, Folder 1656)
          Translated from English by Witold Kalinowski.
        - Lucifer unemployed, by Aleksander Wat (foreword by Miłosz, Polish language version), draft, holograph, 1990 (Box 115, Folder 1657)
        - "Ładne kpiny," draft, holograph, corrected, 1953 (Box 115, Folder 1658)
        - "Mały program,"draft, holograph, corrected, 1957 (Box 115, Folder 1659)
        - "Manfred Kridl," draft, typescript carbon, 1957 (Box 115, Folder 1660)
        - "Maria Dąbrowska: Zaczynając od Klamath," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1962 (Box 115, Folder 1661)
        - "Marx trochę mniej znany," draft, holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 115, Folder 1662)
        - "Metafizyczna pauza," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, and typescript (copy), 1980 (Box 115, Folder 1663-1664)
        - Miałem tylko jedno życie by Teodor Klon (review by Miłosz), draft, typescript, corrected, 1958 (Box 115, Folder 1665)
        - "Miejsca utracone," draft, copy of typescript, corrected, circa 1992 (Box 115, Folder 1666)
        - "Mój 'Litewski Paszport'," draft, copy of typescript, corrected and printed version, 1989 (Box 115, Folder 1667)
        - "Mówiąc o ssaku," draft, holograph, corrected, 1955 (Box 115, Folder 1668)
        - "Nacjonalizm i Bałtowie," draft, copy of typescript, corrected and printed version, 1993 (Box 115, Folder 1669)
          Translation by Elżbieta Sawicka and Miłosz of "Swing shift in the Baltics."
        - "Nad książką czyli Cudze chwalicie" (review of Wiersze Wybrane by Jarosław Iwaszkiewicz), typescript carbon, corrected, 1948 (Box 115, Folder 1670)
        - The Naked and the Dead, by Norman Mailer (review), partial draft, typescript carbon, 1949 (Box 115, Folder 1671)
        - "Nie," draft, holograph, corrected, 1951 (Box 115, Folder 1672)
        - "Niedziela w Brunnen," partial draft, holograph and copy of 1954 printed version, 1954, undated (Box 115, Folder 1673)
        - "Nobel lecture" (Polish version), drafts, holograph, corrected and copies of typescript, 1980-1981 (Box 115, Folder 1674-1675)
        - "Notatki z lektury" (on Les diables de Loudun by Aldous Huxley), draft, holograph, corrected and copy of 1953 printed version, 1953, undated (Box 115, Folder 1676)
        - "Notatki z lektury" (on Nadberezyńcy by Florian Czernyszewicz), draft, holograph, corrected, 1953 (Box 115, Folder 1677)
        - "Notatnik amerykański" (fragments), draft, holograph, 1950s (Box 115, Folder 1678)
        - "Notatnik: Chicago," draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1948 (Box 115, Folder 1679)
        - "Notatnik nowojorski," drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, corrcted, 1946 (Box 115, Folder 1680)
        - "Noty o Różewiczu," typescript, 1996 (Box 115, Folder 1681)
        - "Nowe zadania poezji polskiej," drafts, holograph, typescript, and copy of 1982 printed version (Box 115, Folder 1682-1683)
        - "Nowoczesność," draft, typescript, 1990s (Box 115, Folder 1684)
        - "O Czapskim," draft, typescript, corrected, 1993 (Box 115, Folder 1685)
        - "O dawnym czasie Kultury ," printout, corrected, 1996 (Box 115, Folder 1686)
        - "O 'Dziennikach' Marii Dąbrowskiej," draft, typescript, corrected, 1980s (Box 115, Folder 1687)
        - "O Hemingway'u," draft, typescript carbon, 1946 (Box 116, Folder 1688)
        - "O Josifie Brodskim," draft, typescript, circa 1998 (Box 116, Folder 1689)
          Translated from the English. Foreword to Joseph Brodsky, Leningrad: fragments, by Mikhail Lemkhin.
        - "O konflikcie polsko-litewskim," drafts, holograph and copy of typescript, corrected, 1989 (Box 116, Folder 1690)
        - "O listach Zygmunta," draft, typescript, circa 1992 (Box 116, Folder 1691)
        - "O logice, mistrzyni życia," draft, holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 116, Folder 1692)
        - "O nacjonalizmie," draft, copy of typescript, corrected, 1980s (Box 116, Folder 1693)
          Translation by Hanna Bartoszewicz of "On nationalism," corrected by Miłosz.
        - "O nagrodzie dla Joanny Pollakówny," printout, undated (Box 116, Folder 1694)
        - "O naszej Europie," drafts, holograph and copy of typescript, corrected, 1986 (Box 116, Folder 1695)
          Translated from English. Based on a lecture at the University of Michigan, January 21, 1986.
        - "O Neli Micińskiej," draft, typescript, corrected, 1990s (Box 116, Folder 1696)
        - "O niewiedzy, wyuczonej i literackiej," draft, copy of typescript, corrected, 1980 (Box 116, Folder 1697)
          For an English language version, see "On ignorance, learned and literary."
        - "O poezji St. John Perse'a," draft, holograph, corrected, 1949 (Box 116, Folder 1698)
        - "O poezji w Polsce," draft, holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 116, Folder 1699)
        - "O polskiej poezji," draft, holograph, corrected, 1964 (Box 116, Folder 1700)
        - "O rubryce 'narodowość'," printout, corrected, 1994 (Box 116, Folder 1701)
        - "O Tadeuszu i Irenie Byrskich,"draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 116, Folder 1702)
        - "O wierszach Jastruna," draft, holograph, corrected, 1953 (Box 116, Folder 1703)
        - "O wstydzie i agresji," draft, holograph, corrected, 1962 (Box 116, Folder 1704)
        - "O wygnaniu," draft, copy of typescript, corrected, undated (Box 116, Folder 1705)
          Translated from English ("On exile") by Miłosz.
        - "Oby inaczej," drafts, holograph and copy of typescript, corrected, 1985 (Box 116, Folder 1706)
        - "Obyczaje," draft, typescript carbon, 1950 (Box 116, Folder 1707)
        - "Od tłumacza," draft, holograph, corrected, 1940s (Box 116, Folder 1708)
        - "Odpowiedzi," draft, holograph, 1959 (Box 116, Folder 1709)
        - "Odpowiedź na ankietę" (on Polish-Lithuanian relations) drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1947 (Box 116, Folder 1710-1711)
          Includes a post script.
        - "Odwrót Krasińskiego," drafts, holograph, corrected, typescript carbon, corrected and copy of typescript, corrected, 1959, undated (Box 116, Folder 1712-1713)
        - "Ogród nauk. Polonistyka," draft, holograph and copy of typescript, circa 1978 (Box 116, Folder 1714)
        - On Socialist Realism, by Abram Tertz (introduction by Miłosz, Polish language version), drafts, holograph, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, circa 1959 (Box 116, Folder 1715)
        - "Opowieści pana Guze," typescript of the memoirs of Zygmunt Guze, 1970s (Box 116, Folder 1716)
          Guze's memoirs were excerpted in the essay.
        - "Ostatni świadek," draft, typescript, corrected, circa 1998 (Box 116, Folder 1717)
        - "Ostrzeżenie," draft, typescript carbon, circa 1958 (Box 116, Folder 1718)
        - "Un païen devant la Nouvelle Foi" (Polish language version), draft, holograph, 1951 (Box 116, Folder 1719)
        - Pan Tadeusz, by Adam Mickiewicz, (introduction by Miłosz, Polish language version), drafts, holograph and copy of typescript, corrected, 1992 (Box 116, Folder 1720-1721)
          Includes a copy of a draft of Robert Bourgois's French translation of Pan Tadeusz and corresondence with Editions Noir sur Blanc.
        - "Państwo wyznaniowe?," draft, holograph, 1991 (Box 117, Folder 1722)
        - "Pieniądz," copy of typescript, corrected, 1980s (Box 117, Folder 1723)
        - "Po Noblu," draft, typescript, corrected, 1980 (Box 117, Folder 1724)
        - Po stronie pamięci: Wybór esejow, by Stanisław Vincenz (introduction by Miłosz), draft, holograph, corrected, 1965 (Box 117, Folder 1725)
        - "Pochwała nowości," draft, holograph, corrected, 1940s (Box 117, Folder 1726)
        - Podróż albo Rzeź niewiniątek, by Charles Merrill (introduction by Miłosz), copy of 1996 printed version, 1997 (Box 117, Folder 1727)
        - "Poeta i państwo," draft, holograph and copy of printed version, 1996 (Box 117, Folder 1728-1729)
          Includes a copy of "Geniusz i poeta," by Anatoly Naiman (printed version).
        - "Poeta pieśnarz" (on Franciszek Andruszewicz), draft, holograph, corrected, 1950 (Box 117, Folder 1730)
        - "Poeta w Lemurii," draft, typescript, 1995 (Box 117, Folder 1731)
        - "Poezja jako świadomość," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 117, Folder 1732)
        - "Pogodne pejzaże" (fragments), typescript, 1993 (Box 117, Folder 1733)
        - "Polonistyka," draft, copy of typescript, corrected, circa 1978 (Box 117, Folder 1734)
        - "Polska odpowiedź Albertowi Camus," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1957 (Box 117, Folder 1735)
        - "Polska w awangardzie," draft, copy of typescript, 1980s (Box 117, Folder 1736)
        - "Pomnik," draft, holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 117, Folder 1737)
        - Postwar Polish Poetry, edited by Miłosz (commentary), draft, holograph, corrected, 1965 (Box 117, Folder 1738)
        - "Powikłania jednej porażki," drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, 1963 (Box 117, Folder 1739-1740)
        - "Proza" (on Jerzy Stempowski), draft, typescript, corrected, 1961 (Box 117, Folder 1741)
        - "Próba porozumienia," draft, typescript carbon, 1956 (Box 117, Folder 1742)
        - "Próba ujawnienia," drafts, holograph, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, 1962 (Box 117, Folder 1743-1744)
          Also printed as "Jeffers: próba ujawnienia"
        - "Prywatne obowiązki wobec polskiej literatury" (postscript), draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1969 (Box 117, Folder 1745)
        - "Przemówienie w Gettysburgu" (translation of the Gettysburg Address), drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1989-1990 (Box 117, Folder 1746)
          Includes a letter from Richard Lourie.
        - "Przygody poezji nowoczesnej" (fragment), typescript carbon, corrected, 1961 (Box 117, Folder 1747)
        - "Przypis do listu Jerzego Stempowskiego z 14.I.1966," drafts, holograph, typescript and copy of typescript, corrected, undated (Box 117, Folder 1748)
          For a related publication in English, see "On chance and research."
          Alternate title: "Komentarz do listu z 14.I.66."
        - "Punkt widzenia, czyli o tak zwanej drugiej awangardzie," draft, holograph, 1966 (Box 117, Folder 1749)
          Alternate title: "Punkt widzenia, czyli mała autobiografia poetycka"
        - "Radość i poezja," drafts, holograph, typescript and copy of typescript, corrected, circa 1992 (Box 117, Folder 1750-1751)
        - "Raport zupełnie suchy," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1947 (Box 117, Folder 1752)
          Alternate title: "Książki i pisma w Stanach Zjednoczonych."
        - "Rivière," drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected, 1952 (Box 118, Folder 1753)
        - "Robinson Jeffers: Fragment rozmowy," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1963 (Box 118, Folder 1754)
        - "Rodziewiczówna," draft, holograph, corrected, 1991 (Box 118, Folder 1755)
        - "Rozmyślania w hotelowym hallu," draft, typescript, 1947 (Box 118, Folder 1756)
        - "Rysunek z pamięci/ Koniec tygodnia," draft, holograph, corrected, 1948 or 1949 (Box 118, Folder 1757)
        - "Science fiction i przyjście Antychrysta," draft, holograph, corrected and copy of 1970 printed version, 1970, undated (Box 118, Folder 1758)
        - "Siła przyzwyczajenia," draft, holograph, 1956 (Box 118, Folder 1759)
        - "Skoki temperatury," drafts, holograph, corrected, circa 1956 (Box 118, Folder 1760)
          Alternate title: "Wymarsz z czarnej groty"
        - "Spotkania," draft, holograph, corrected, 1954 (Box 118, Folder 1761)
        - "Sprawa stylu," draft, holograph, corrected, 1949 (Box 118, Folder 1762)
        - "Sprzeczność w życiu i dziele Mickiewicza," draft, typescript carbon, 1955 (Box 118, Folder 1763)
          Translated from the French (untitled speech at an evening dedicated to Adam Mickiewicz).
        - "Stereotyp Conrada," draft, typescript carbon, 1957 (Box 118, Folder 1764)
        - "Streszczenie scenariusza 'Sea is my destination'" (summary of a screenplay about Joseph Conrad), drafts, typescript, corrected, 1930s (Box 118, Folder 1765)
        - "Swedenborg i Dostojewski," draft, typescript, corrected, printed versions, and copy of printed version, 1976-1978, undated (Box 118, Folder 1766-1767)
        - "Szestow albo czystość rozpaczy," draft, typescript, corrected, circa 1973 (Box 118, Folder 1768)
          Translation from the English by Miłosz of "Shestov, or the purity of despair"
        - "Szlachetność, niestety," drafts, holograph and copy of typescript, corrected, and copy of printed version, 1984 (Box 118, Folder 1769)
          Based on a lecture at a conference on "Contemporary Poland in Historical Perspective," Yale University
        - "Śmiech i trochę zgrozy," draft, typescript, 1990s (Box 118, Folder 1770)
        - "Śmierć Józefa Sadzika," draft, holograph, corrected, 1980 (Box 118, Folder 1771)
        - "Tadeusz Hollender," draft, holograph, corrected, 1953 or 1954 (Box 118, Folder 1772)
        - "Teodor Bujnicki (Portrety polskich poetów)," drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected, 1954 (Box 118, Folder 1773)
        - "Tygrys," draft, typescript, corrected, circa 1959 (Box 118, Folder 1774)
        - "Venclova," holograph, undated (Box 118, Folder 1775)
        - "Visitez la diaspora," draft, holograph, corrected, 1960s (Box 118, Folder 1776)
        - "W dolinie Taos," draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1948 (Box 118, Folder 1777)
        - "W Polsce 1950 roku" (on Le moissonneur d'épines by Georges Govy), draft, typescript carbon, corrected, circa 1956 (Box 118, Folder 1778)
        - "W stronę kobiet," drafts, holograph and printout, corrected, 1993 (Box 118, Folder 1779)
        - "W Wielkim Księstwie Sillicianii," draft, typescript, corrected, and copy of proof, corrected, 1988-1991 (Box 118, Folder 1780-1781)
        - "Wspomnienie," draft, typescript, 1990s (Box 118, Folder 1782)
        - "Wykład o nihilizmie," draft, holograph, corrected, 1940s (Box 118, Folder 1783)
        - "Z poezją polską przeciw światu," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1989 (Box 119, Folder 1784)
          For an English language version, see "With Polish poetry against the World."
        - "Zakończenie," draft, typescript, corrected, circa 1961 (Box 119, Folder 1785)
        - "Zamiar," draft, holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 119, Folder 1786)
        - "Zamiast życzen urodzinowych," draft, typescript, corrected, 1996 (Box 119, Folder 1787)
        - Zaraz po wojnie. Korespondencja z pisarzami 1945-1950 (preface by Miłosz), printout, 1998 (Box 119, Folder 1788)
        - "Zderzenia literackie: O Staffa; Bez taryfy ulgowej; Gastronomia; O Gombrowicza," draft, holograph, corrected, 1957 (Box 119, Folder 1789)
        - Znad Świtezi w głąb Tajgi: rozmowy z moją matką, by Grażyna Strumiłło-Miłosz (preface by Czesław Miłosz), printout, 1993 (Box 119, Folder 1790)
        - "Życie w U.S.A.," draft, typescript carbon, 1947 (Box 119, Folder 1791)
        - Untitled and unidentified works
          - Fragmenty z Szopki akademickiej w Wilnie, notes in an unidenfied hand, 1931-1932 (Box 119, Folder 1792)
          - "Ktokolwiek przekracza prog galerii sztuki Art of this Century ...," drafts, holograph and typescript, 1947 (Box 119, Folder 1793)
          - "Książka, która oddaję do druku ..." (introduction to an anthology of English poetry), holograph, circa 1948 (Box 119, Folder 1794)
          - "Sądzę, że napisanie wyczerpującego komentarza ..." (introduction to an anthology of poetry), holograph, circa 1948 (Box 119, Folder 1795)
          - "Jeżdżąc tego lata po Polsce ..." (on plastic arts in Poland), holograph, 1949 (Box 119, Folder 1796)
          - "Niedawno toczyła się na łamach naszych pism ...," holograph, circa 1950 (Box 119, Folder 1797)
          - "Książka O sytuacji w historii literatury polskiej ...," holograph, circa 1951 (Box 119, Folder 1798)
          - "Otrzmalem list od redaktora Kultury " (on Polish poetry during the Second World War), draft, holograph, corrected, 1953 (Box 119, Folder 1799)
          - "Oglądanie mapy Europy ..." (on the year 1952), typescript carbon, corrected, circa 1953 (Box 119, Folder 1800)
          - "Rzeczy dziwne ..." (on Jeanne Hersch and Zniewolony umysł ), draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1953 (Box 119, Folder 1801)
          - "Staram się zdać sobie sprawę z zadań ...," holograph, 1953 (Box 119, Folder 1802)
          - "W ciągu ostatnich paru lat ...," holograph, circa 1953 (Box 119, Folder 1803)
          - "Tłumaczenia literatury amerykańskiej ...," holograph, circa 1954 (Box 119, Folder 1804)
          - "Ziema jest miejscem doskonałej ..." (beginning of an autobiographical novel), typescript, circa 1956 (Box 119, Folder 1805)
            Includes material that was printed in Rodzinna Europa.
          - "Materiał obserwacji zebranych ...," holograph, circa 1957 (Box 119, Folder 1806)
          - "Pamphilia spożywała swoje sery w spokoju ...," holograph, corrected, circa 1959 (Box 119, Folder 1807)
          - "Jest to sprawa naszej obecności ...," holograph, 1959-1960 (Box 119, Folder 1808)
          - "Antologia współczesnej poezji i prozy greckiej ...," holograph, 1950s (Box 119, Folder 1809)
          - "Dwadzieścia sześć lat temu umarł człowiek ...," (on Joseph Conrad), typescript carbon, 1950s (Box 119, Folder 1810)
          - "Historia literatury polskiej ..." (possibly written for a French encyclopedia), typescript carbon, 1950s (Box 119, Folder 1811)
          - "Kretowa chodziła po pokojach," holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 119, Folder 1812)